Guide to the Robert Olsen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert Olsen papers
1995-2014
WA MSS S-3230
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12.75
(10 boxes)
The Robert Olsen Papers contain sketchbooks, notebooks, ephemera, and artwork documenting Olsen's artistic practice.
Olsen, Robert, 1969-2014
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert Olsen, Sr., 2017.
2017 acquisition: Gift of Robert Olsen, Sr. and Katie Michel, 2017.
2018 acquisition: Purchased from PH Gallery Holdings, LLC on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana Fund, 2018.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Sketchbooks, 1995-2012. II. Notebooks, 1999-2013. III. Artwork, 2014. IV. 2017 acquisition, 2013-2014. V. 2018 acquisition, 2009, undated.
Robert Olsen
Robert Olsen, an artist known for his paintings and drawings of Los Angeles, was born in Turlock, California in 1969. After receiving a BFA from California College of Arts and Craft and an MFA from University of California, Los Angeles, Olsen settled in Los Angeles, California. From 2000 until his death in 2014, Olsen exhibited his artwork in galleries in the United States and internationally.
Custodial History
The Robert Olsen Papers contains material donated by Olsen's parents, Sandy Olsen and Robert Olsen, Sr.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Olsen Papers, which span from 1995 to 2014, contain sketchbooks, notebooks, ephemera, and artwork documenting Olsen's artistic practice.
Art, American -- 20th Century; Art, American -- 21st century; Artists -- United States -- Archives; Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Art, Modern -- 21st century; Paintings (visual works); Sketchbooks; Drawings (visual works); Artists -- United States -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States -- 21st century; Olsen, Robert, 1969-2014
- Sketchbooks, 1995-2012; Series I
  Arrangement
  Sketchbooks are arranged chronologically. Undated sketchbooks are filed after dated materials.
  Scope and Contents
  Sketchbooks contain drawings and notes created during Robert Olsen's artistic practice. Some sketchbooks include loose pages, photographs, artist statements, and laid-in ephemera.
  - Sketchbook, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbooks, 2000; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Sketchbook, 2010 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2010-2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2010-2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011-2012 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2011-2012 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2012 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbook, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Sketchbook, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Sketchbook, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Sketchbook, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Sketchbook, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 22 volumes (Box 3)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 22 volumes (Box 4)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 13 volumes (Box 5)
- Notebooks, 1999-2013; Series II
  Notesbooks are arranged chronologically. Undated notebooks are filed after dated materials.
  Notebooks contain writings by Robert Olsen, largely generated during Olsen's artistic practice. Some notebooks include loose pages, photographs, sketches, and laid-in ephemera.
  - Notebook with three loose photographs, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2001 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2006 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2010 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 2013 (Box 5)
  - Notebook with loose sketch, undated (Box 5)
  - Notebook with loose art booklets, undated (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, undated; 10 volumes (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, undated; 35 volumes (Box 6)
- Artwork, 2014; Series III; 2.25; (1 box)
  This item is an in-progress version of a Robert Olsen painting entitled "Overpass #2".
  - Overpass #2, 2014 (Box 7 (Oversize))